hello
everyone welcome to team com active
stream
number 3.5 this is a follow-up
discussion
from number three a world unto itself
and welcome everybody so thanks again to
yvonne and alex for coming to this
discussion and thanks to shannon
for coming again hi everyone
cool i'm gonna share our slides and
we'll get
right into it this is team com 3.5
welcome to team com for our first time
or not first time
listeners this is a recorded
and archived live stream we as team com
are an experiment in online team
communication and learning related to
active inference
you can reach us through twitter email
our public key base team or our youtube
channel
we welcome all skills backgrounds and
perspectives
and we ask for our conversions to
use good online video chat etiquette to
be respectful
muting and raising your hands and also
everyone please provide us with feedback
so we can
improve our work today in
active inference stream number 3.5 which
is a follow-up to number three
discussing the same paper
we're going to have a quick check check
in and warm up as usual
and then we'll return to our discussion
of the paper
and we've obtained a bunch of follow-up
questions
from ourselves and some colleagues and
we've sorted them loosely into
a couple of categories and we'll be able
to take
questions about any topic but the slides
are somewhat organizing the questions
into topics of communication
development attunement attention and
free energy itself
so as far as the check-in and warm-up
the first question
is what is an interesting type of
communication you've experienced or
maybe even thought about
in the previous week
um for me it was a meeting with my
relatives what i didn't had a chance
to see about for half a year before
because of koid and so on so his
last weekend was quite happy meeting
with relatives and some kind of
discussion and so it's an attunement
between us after a long time
cool and maybe either ivan or shannon in
related to that answer
how has going remote or just this
situation of
the past year influenced your style of
communication or relating
sure so yesterday we had our first
meeting of our graduate student group
and we had about 40 people in one zoom
room
and after a whole summer of seeing maybe
four or five different faces
on a screen and being able to make sure
eye contact with whoever you're talking
to um
yesterday was a bit of a bombardment of
like visual sensory information
like searching for the person who was
speaking and
trying to tune out like the extra
movements or
drinks of a water bottle or like
someone's
pet on screen while also trying to pay
attention to if someone had like a nod
or raised their actual
physical hand in a video it was
definitely an adjustment like
oh i was a lot more conscious of
all of the interactions of everyone on
the screen than i would have been had we
been in a room
in person
yeah there's big differences between
being with three people in a room and
and 40 people in a room and so it
shouldn't be surprising that there's
differences between the kind of smaller
video chat that we're having here and
then the larger scale rooms but it's
really hard to stay on top of everything
when we don't get the full information
and then
i guess a last general question what is
something that
is new that you've experienced or
learned about this week
if anyone has thoughts or we can just
continue
yvonne i i can tell that
in our company we have a frequent
meeting each monday morning we discuss
about work issues and
this week i
i saw that the meeting goes
different when different number of
people
um
different number of people
involved in in this meeting
and it's very interesting
why people who
who is absent now how do they
influence the meeting
and maybe they don't know
about that they influence yeah
of while they are absent
interesting yeah with organizations
people can have
influence whether they're in the room or
not so sometimes the communication
ecology of the meeting room includes
like
people who are in a different room
fundamentally
and then also because communication is
so non-additive it's non-linear
if you have a certain outcome with
person abc and they have a dance party
and then you take away person c and
there's no dance party that doesn't mean
that person c
you know is the dance party it just
means there's some sort of emergent
outcome with the three people who were
there
and there's a different emerging outcome
when somebody isn't there
so how do we deal with that this
non-linearity of communication
and maybe even this paper might have
some
ideas so we are continuing our
discussion
of vasel at all 2020 a world unto itself
human communication as active inference
and
last time in our stream number three we
went
over the goals the abstract the figures
and a few of the big ideas
of the paper welcome sasha
this time we're going to be asking some
follow-up questions and having
continued discussion about the paper and
so
our first topic will be communication
and these were compiled
questions from a bunch of people who
submitted them to us
or some things that we wanted to address
in the first stream but didn't get a
chance
so anyone is welcome to pop in with
whatever they want to say about one of
the questions or
uh follow up with an additional question
but we'll just release them one by one
so we can stay um
at least on topic with what we're
talking about up
maybe not here let's go to the first one
so i think this was alex your
question there's cooperative competitive
or adversarial
communication and there's other kinds of
communication too possibly
so what are the kinds of communication
that can be identified
and how
what made you ask this question or what
what would be interesting to know about
this
because the paper
the paper what we are reading is about
uh
cooperative communication and everything
is about it
but also it mentioned that it's possible
and it's
really true it's it's possible what
communication could be competitive in
some situation
between two people between teams
and the question is what our types
could be to be identified maybe some
kind of
mix of these two types and
in case when communication is happening
how it is possible maybe to understand
if it's really cooperative or it's
changed in competitive in some moment
great question and is cooperative
communication
about the ends if it results in
cooperative behavior
is that cooperative communication or
does cooperative communication
entail turn-taking and feeling of
cooperation
because the feeling of cooperation and
turn-taking can be
hijacked or used non-cooperatively let's
just say
and then the sort of allswell that
enswell approach
might excuse some extremely
inappropriate communication
mechanics in service of the cooperative
end goal but who's cooperative end goal
and how are they defining that
so it's a big question like do we define
communication
by the mechanism and the details of the
conversation itself or do we define it
by the context
so if we uh consider it for uh
from some again from an engineering
point
now we need to have some kind of
approaches to manage communication
and to control it during its way
to have predicted
or expect results from it
yep and i think that the general message
passing or information sharing
frameworks
are almost broader than cooperation
itself the
communication outline that's uh inactive
inference
could be between a person and a tiger
and
that whether it's cooperative or not
could be kind of a lens that you apply
to it
but the signals are certainly moving
between the communicating agents
whether they think they're cooperating
or they actually are so
communication is sort of the the
fundamental
and then all these other adjectives get
layered on top depending on how we think
about that kind of communication
any other thoughts on that first part
so and if if somebody wants to they can
always jump back or
add non-sequiturs but we'll continue
yeah i wanted to
uh add briefly um and then thinking in
the context of
uh long-term collaboration um
it seems like communication would have
to um
have signs of cooperativity at every
stage along the way
because there is no end that is obvious
or
um you know if you want a long-term
collaboration
you don't want it to end because of a
miscommunication
and how to focus on
that kind of positive feedback without
sinking into
kind of the superficial um signs of
cooperation
of where people simply feel that it is
cooperative
nice good point this
second quote speaks to that a little bit
it says a single individual
is necessary to obtain a low risk
and low reward and then collaboration
appears as a riskier but
more rewarding option so this is kind of
within that
prisoner's dilemma type game theory
where
individuals are whether it's individual
cells or
eagles or birds or some other thing it's
being
phrased as a question of action for the
individual
whether they want to go their own way
whether that's considered defecting or
it's just the baseline state to be
individuated and obtained with a higher
probability a smaller reward
like i could work for ten dollars an
hour by myself
or collaboration um opens the door to
potentially
win-win collaborations where you make uh
on
average more than ten dollars an hour
because you worked with multiple people
and you allowed your specialization and
your perspectives to
contribute to your shared value however
it may be the case that
this collaboration is also riskier
and so i think alex again you asked what
types of risk can be identified
in a communicative setting and how could
we quantify
such risks especially if we were going
to quantify them using the way of
thinking of active inference
um yes uh again it's about for me
if we speak about collaboration and
collaboration is based on communication
and first risk is
not to have uh alignment
at the end of communication but what uh
possible kind of risks could be arised
additionally
for example to take
wrong direction for communication and
maybe if such kind of list could be
prepared
if there are any possible way to
quantify it
in terms of
active inference framework and in terms
of
i don't know
maybe some kind of epistemic values
or something like this
um to i have a bit of an addition to
that
um to to bring it back to fep
and minimization of uncertainty um
how do we determine kind of a good
enough alignment
like something that is appropriate for
the goal
um because you could imagine that
there's
collaborations where you don't feel very
aligned but it's a low stakes
situation and at the start and at the
end
you feel that you know your values or um
goals weren't really aligned but you
still did the task that you were
trying to do um and and perhaps that's
that's not
the best case scenario but it's a
realistic one
yep and de-risking communication so for
example
uh and there's many kinds of risks that
can be identified so maybe i'll
start with that like there's the risk
that you end up trusting somebody who
ends up
leaking your information or directly um
causing an action to you or to a project
that is deleterious
somebody who causes your time to be
spent inefficiency
inefficiently um there's all these kinds
of
risks of biting off a bigger chunk with
the help of a team
but then the chunk that you bite off is
the wrong one or you fail to bite off
the chunk if it is the right one
and then how do we quantify so much i
like that
idea alex of course sort of like a
checklist manifesto
but from the active inference potential
uh potential
uh applications and asking
more specifically uh what what kinds of
things can we discuss as a team
that reduce our uncertainty about this
and this and this
and i think that's definitely one of the
directions we're moving so maybe we can
keep that kind of question in mind
and think about what are these best
practices for teams at
the onset or in the middle or in the
closing of
even a little phase of their
collaboration what are these questions
or provocations that teams could take on
that would de-risk their communication
and improve the throughput
potentially in a way that could be
lending itself towards being formalized
yeah i have a thought on that um this
kind of sounds
like the uh the grace's maxims
where um what you say like in
communication
one maximum is like relevance it needs
to be relevant to
um the conversation or to whatever
you're referring to
um and i think it's either quantity or
quality where you
need to say just enough that your
message gets across
but not too much um and this is like
also something that you're
inferring on your communicative partner
very cool i looked up these uh grice's
maxims
g-r-i-c-e is the last name and the four
of them just to
clarify the maxim of quantity which is
be as informative as you possibly can
without any more information than needed
the maxim of quality
which is being truthful and not giving
information that's false or not
supported by evidence
the maxim of relation where one tries to
be relevant
and say things that are pertinent to
discussion and then the maxim
of manner is the fourth and last one
where one tries to be
clear brief and orderly without
obscurity or ambiguity
so these are really interesting it
reminds me of
the truth the whole truth nothing but
the truth from the
justice system and also these are these
are great reminders
in all sorts of communication especially
ones
that are potentially recorded or for a
consumption
where the kinds of vocal pauses that
are played off as irrelevancies in
conversation
become magnified a lot and good public
speaking is a challenge because
having these cognitive maxims at the top
of our mind
prevents us from thinking the topic
itself unless it's a situation
thankfully where you're talking about
the maximums themselves
so it's hard to speak directly and with
high uh
relevantness and quality and
quantitativity
when all these other things are
happening so very
interesting connection there and it
would be a way to de-risk communication
by using these maxims
so third point here communicative
constructions
we'll just use cc are patterned pairings
of form and meaning
could we formally join communicative
constructions with narrative and
ontologies
or what other kinds of cc could we use
yeah as for this question is uh
communicative construction uh looks like
uh well well-developed uh area
and it's defines uh pairing
of forms and meaning so it could be
different forms
and it's always i think connect to some
meaning
and as we develop in our
directions and discuss his narratives
and
ontologies if we'll find a way to
joint it with uh communicative
construction and define it this way
it could be more useful to discuss with
other parties
so and the next uh step is
what our types of construction
could we see or defined or find
else to be formal
so we could use it in more efficient way
nice it reminds me of just regular
constructions and there are specific
kinds of constructions there's bridges
and doorways and
all these things and sometimes there's
overlap or there's an object that's a
chair
and a bridge because you can sit on it
but the point is they're still
constructed
and so when we're talking about
communicative constructs
like turn taking or these other like
what is a bridge
for communication what are these
constructs that are
not just there in nature waiting to be
discovered but what are these constructs
that we're going to implement in the
world
ideally to get from here to there to get
from not knowing to
knowing and what are these constructs
and what would be an ontology
or a framework for the knowledge to
discuss these kinds of constructs
instead of just saying well it's a
discussion there's no more detail i can
provide then it's a discussion
are there types of discussion are there
types of dialogue that might be able to
be more useful in one place or another
just like a bridge would make sense here
but not here
so cool question and then last question
on the communication slide
there was a note about diversification
of communicative systems
across time space and speaker
communities
as well as species we could add which
communication systems
can be identified in relationship to
teams and organizations
yes and again for me it's open question
and
trying to see perspective to
have this uh
approach to describe
possible way and possible communication
systems
what could be useful for teams and
organization
and here as we see is related to time
and space
and so it could be about time scales
and uh organization also could be
possible like space
and could be present in different
countries so we still need to
have options to communicate and so
define system
in use for it
so it's directions for future
development of our work
cool any other notes on that
just from the chat and this was in
response i believe to something
that sasha mentioned about how good is
good enough for the team
rj wrote because there are opportunities
for signal error
can the longevity of cooperation be
assessed by goodness of fit between
self-reporting of participants concerns
about risk of miscommunication and so
this is a pretty meta
comment it's asking instead of a let's
say an annual
progress checkup on how happy or how
satisfied and if the satisfaction is
going up
then it's getting better if the
satisfaction's going down it's getting
worse
this is like asking the participants to
self-report
on their perception of the risk of
miscommunication
and so you could ask the employee how
well do you think
the communication channel is between you
and your supervisor or vice versa
and then by potentially uh maintaining
the longevity of the group
which is a success in and of itself
because of the many opportunities
for failure of groups beyond longevity
we could actually
improve the self-report of the precision
of the communication
rather than trying to do this ultimately
futile
optimization on satisfaction because
that's a moving target
but something that we can latch on to is
precise communication
and precise communication within the
context of an aligned
narrative for the team or the
organization would
ultimately potentially lead to
satisfaction so interesting
point by rj any thoughts before we move
forward
cool so this is what you all came here
for
someone was told there would be baby
pictures on the stream
here's a quote from the paper to get us
thinking about
development they wrote human infants
only appear satisfied following a
communicative bid
when their own communicative partner has
aligned their mental states with their
own
with respect to the infant's intended
referent and some
citations there to follow so what does
that
quotation mean or what does anyone think
about that
here's the questions that we can ask
about development
um the first question is how or when
does a child learn to align mental
states to satisfy communicative bids
the second question and what we can you
wanna
does anyone have thoughts on the first
question
um yeah i
um kind of as a corollary to um
yeah as i was reading it i was really
trying to parse through
the development of this process um uh
like the the ontogeny of it and
because there is
a maturation of how cooperative
communication happens
that um
there should also be a start when you
learn to align your mental states
but of course upon reading the paper
again and um
you know working through all the baby
references
um the author states that
you never actually learn to do this
process it's part of the
adaptive priors for alignment that
humans are endowed with
so um perhaps i can already answer that
first question
so what the answer is how or when uh the
when it sounds like
it's continuous it's always a continuous
process
and then how is kind of the broad
topic of development how does language
develop how does culture develop
and then i thought the point that you
made about in
evolutionary prior is very good and it's
also a challenging
question to ask what exactly this prior
is and that's why so much of the paper
is about it
because it's pretty clear that we don't
have a prior
for any specific language in the sense
that a baby who
is growing up around no language will
fail to develop
uh linguistic capabilities in this same
whereas
any child raised in a different
linguistic setting will take on
that language so there's a prior that
language will be
communicated but it's almost a prior
that's above the level of the specific
language
yet there seem to be things about our
evolutionary prior
like grammar or structure or certain
types of logical relationships that are
harder
um to change shannon
not to be contrarian but i'm going to be
a little contrarian
is um we talk a lot about um language or
maybe there's some innate prior that
will develop
language but there's something that
happens even before language and that's
the rhythm
of development like in the womb so you
have these bipedal
rhythms of the mothers walking you have
rhythms of the heartbeat breathing
rhythms
and these are these like very embodied
forms of not necessarily communication
at that stage but it is signaling
um to the infant in the womb like
whether the situation is
stressful or not for the mother and thus
for the
um uh not yet or an infant and then once
you're born you're holding the infant
there's a lot of you know skin-to-skin
contact so you're still maintaining this
um not quite communication but this
balance of the mother's
heart rhythms or breathing rhythms to
the infants and then slowly
externalizing that
to um gaze relationships or
to like when you're playing with the
baby's hands you know you're holding
their hands maybe moving them
and then slowly just externalizing these
rhythms into
more and more communicative acts and
less sort of direct embodied
relationships
cool yvonne
uh i wanted to say that toddlers
has have very
very limited
[Music]
limited set of mental states
and to to align
with its
state
their vis-a-vis
came to do this alignment
more simple rather than
we talk about all the people who
has more broad
mental states more more broad set of
their internal states
yep and we can come back to that when we
get to the attunement
question shannon i i really liked how
you described
the continuum from the really the
communication that is related to rhythm
of the heart and the intrigue maybe
circadian rhythms in the blood
so very slow rhythms and rhythms that
are transmitted through
tactile stimulus through the womb as
well as chemical or
neural type relationships and then it's
like this gradual disconnection
where as the physical touch is replaced
by the gaze
and then adults tend to have more of a
barrier
physically between them at least that's
coming from a culturally specific
place but maybe it still does hold it's
rare to see adults
touching each other as much as for
example a mother and an infant
and so this second question how does it
relate
this development of communication
through these different modalities
and from things that barely seem
communicative things that almost seem
physiological
but then in the end if we're
communicating about what's for dinner
isn't that also a physiological
communication that reduces our
uncertainty about where nutrition is
coming from
so is it that different than a uh
pre-linguistic
cry for milk and then how does it relate
to this
way in which adults understand each
other
and then it reminds me also of these
different modalities of
therapy um and even thinking about like
maslow's hierarchy of needs
the idea that the end-all be-all is the
linguistic expression
i'm sorry or uh i'm happy that's kind of
the tip of the iceberg
for linguistically capable adults but
what is that
embodied iceberg what is the actual
thing
that we're trying to communicate what's
the territory not just the linguistic
map
and then how does this relate to the
communication or other issues that
adults have
and we want to work it out and then are
we going to use our words
are we going to use our uh lower
levels of the massless hierarchy lower
chakras we get physical
for better or for worse
and just to get to the last question on
this development
slide what are some linguistic
characteristics
of cooperative communication
this this relates a bit to earlier our
discussion
about is cooperative communication
characterized by the mechanics
like polite turn taking or relevant
sharing of information
are they defined by the end goal so
cooperative communication
is all's well that ends well or is it
something
uh else like something ethical or
something normative
like cooperative communication is when
you follow those four maxims of good
communication
even if you're impolite about it or it
leads to a non-cooperative end
for who as long as you abide by these
conversational rules
then it's going to be a cooperative
communication
what what are some of these linguistic
characteristics if any or
what are the characteristics of
cooperative communication that go beyond
linguistics
cool oh go ahead sasha um
yeah kind of
well yeah sort of relevant to this
question but the the first
uh question on the side made me think
about
um other
alternative
states or abilities of communication
so that children who
grow up not being able to hear or
speak or see for any number of
all right looks like we had a brief
little disrupt
and so i'm just going to send a link to
get the rest of our colleagues back
into here while they
are getting back in i'm going to go back
to
sharing our screen so we were just
having
sasha talking about
the developmental characteristics
of cooperative communication and
yes yep sorry something definitely did
go wrong there but
we're on part two of three point five
three point five
two celavi and
uh we are continuing on the
development slide and well as people
join in we'll be ready to move
on yep sasha something definitely
blipped a little bit uh alex if you
could message
shannon just to make sure that she knows
that we'll use this link
we are back live so continuing with
what you were saying about the
linguistics and cooperation
it's like you knew i was gonna say
something wrong so it cut me off
um um
yeah so to that point i i think the
linguistic characteristics
um at the very least would look like a
back and forth
such that the communication would be
happening
on multiple scales
that people are communicating but also
getting feedback within their short
glimpse of communication
and that kind of reminds me of the
um the checklist or the the multiple
scales of communication for teams that
we brought up earlier
but maybe that's kind of like the baby
steps of developing
communication yep
cool and alex you've
sent the uh message thank you
so let's get to the question of
attunement and whenever
she rejoins we'll just hop in so here's
a quotation
from the paper the hypothesis here
is then that repeated couplings between
infants and children
with adults and more experienced peers
may cause the prior beliefs of
inexperienced
individuals to converge more towards the
hidden causes generating
sensory consequences i.e the mental
states of more experienced others
rather than the other way around that is
coupled action perception cycles in such
dyads
tend to be characterized by an
asymmetric entrainment of prior beliefs
what does this mean what is the most
just foundational interpretation
of this question and then how does this
relate maybe to the infant adult
dyad communication
i'll just start with the base
interpretation so we're talking about
hey shannon welcome back sorry about
that we're talking about
these communicative dyadic situations
between two or multiple agents
and we're referring to one of the
individuals as
more experienced and one of them as
relatively inexperienced
in the context of some niche so it isn't
that one
is closer to absolute truth that's not
that babies are closer to absolute truth
it's not that the adult is closer to
absolute truth
it's that one of these individuals has
had more experience in in a
certain informational niche and also
might have a higher degree of precision
on their beliefs and that could be an
example of this evolutionary
hyper prior which is like the
temperature on decision making
of a young person starts high so you
could tell them
yep the sky is like a fabric and the sun
is carried by a chariot
and that explains it reduces their
uncertainty about the path of the sun in
the sky
and so potentially that is taken up by
the younger
uh or the more inexperienced individual
whereas somebody who had very high
precision on what the sun was
um whether they thought it was a car or
a nuclear reactor or something
that person is going to be harder to
move
into a new narrative and so when you
have an experienced and an inexperienced
individual or for that matter a stubborn
and an open-minded individual
because of the asymmetries you're going
to get this type of asymmetric
uh this differential outcome through the
communication
and here it's being described as the
inexperienced individual converging to
the priors
of the experienced one and not vice
versa so any
thoughts on that one
and this relates to figure 5a which we
discussed in our last discussion but
here we have
the two birds the relatively experienced
one and the inexperienced one
and here experience is represented by a
higher value of this order parameter on
the y-axis
such that a high level of experience in
singing
is correlated with a high order
parameter reflecting a
a very accurate ability to perform turn
taking
and that would relate to optimal flow of
information if the turn taking were
optimal
like if one person started talking right
when the other person stopped talking
and then when we're in this learning
alone paradigm with the shaded
confidence intervals of the two birds we
see that the order
paradigm how order the two birds are
relative to each other
just drops off as a function of bouts of
communication
and we were thinking about this like the
two recording studios
the two individuals are singing a call
and response song but they're not
synchronized
and so through their singing they end up
desynchronizing through no fault of
their own
however when you're having a sensory
coupling
and a deep prior that you want to be
aligned with your conversant or with
your communicative partner
that's learning together you need the
sensory coupling and you also need this
prior that you want to be aligned on
your mindset
and then we see that the blue line
becomes
asymmetrically entrained more to the
green line than the other way around and
we talked about that how the green line
looks a little bit like it's going down
almost like the blue line induces uh
somewhat of a disordering
of the green line and we asked whether
that was reflected or not by the kinds
of communications that we see with
adults and with humans
um any thoughts on this a two-minute
slide we have one more attunement slide
sash uh yeah uh thank you for explaining
that that was a
my question in understanding this uh
rather
long sentence and just getting to
um why
it is building towards the um
the state of the more more experienced
uh
partner rather than the other way around
because
um yeah and
and adding in the the precision of
an open mindedness versus stubbornness
that really helps to
um kind of help better understand why
it's uh moving
in one direction versus the other
because it's um
the parameter like in this graph is not
just an arbitrary value of how much
you're like one
thing or another but it's about your
precision
on what you're doing
shannon yeah um to follow up on that
there's also
like if this was a graph um that was
showing oscillations around the steady
state instead of um
the graph that it is like you might
actually see smaller oscillations in
this top
partner because they're they're sort of
converging on a steady state already
and this blue partner might have like
very wide oscillations until they start
to find
the similar steady state
yes definitely true this is averaged out
and has the confidence interval but then
in the context of real
learning or potentially niche
entrainment it's not just this
by step there's periods of stasis and oh
i get it and then you jump up it's a
quantum
change in comprehension or there's an
overshoot
somebody oh they were too eager on this
one and then they go too far to the
other side
but then we're able to look at the error
residual
and then hopefully reducing the error
is what gets us to precision so a cool
way to
see it here visually let's think a
little bit more about
attunement with this other quote from
the paper
they wrote human individuals appear
characteristically
i.e species typically we can discuss
that to be endowed
with an adaptive prior that one's mental
states are aligned with those of con
specifics
what does that mean just what is the
first level interpretation of that
sentence and then
what about our priors are adaptive can
they
go wrong and then um what about that is
species typical with respect to humans
any thoughts there and i also added
in a replicate of the capheim
figure about tin bergens for questions
just a reminder that we're always
thinking about these multiple versions
of
why at the same time so why do humans do
x or why does x appear in life
these are questions that are going to
have multiple kinds of answers
so we're not looking for an exclusionary
answer we want to understand
whether our answer is actually striking
at the level of causation
of utility of ontogeny development
or at the level of evolution itself
so any thoughts on either responding
within the context of one of these four
squares or just what the sentence means
so in differentiating human
communication
from non-human primate and other species
in the paper
what happened a lot was this discussion
about the humans
wanting to have their mental states
aligned and we
saw that in the previous quote like the
baby isn't satisfied
until the uh mental state is aligned
until it believes that the mental state
is aligned and i think it was shannon um
who brought up
this something where if somebody gets
the right food for you from the grocery
store but you think that they were
misinformed about something else
it's almost like it's not good enough
for us to get what we asked for at the
grocery store
we really want to make sure that they
also knew exactly
at a deeper level why we were wanting
that
and so this question about the humans
being
uh endowed with a prior that we want to
be aligned at a mental state level now
i'll just first start with
the species specific question i wonder
if in a wolf pack
or in uh an ant colony although one
could debate to what extent these mental
states are
aware or something like that that's a
little bit on the
qualia end of the spectrum i would still
say that
in these groups be it insect or other
mammals
these individuals do benefit from having
the mental state of the pack aligned
and so in that respect i wonder if they
also have an adaptive prior that their
mental states would be aligned with con
specifics
that's actually interesting bringing up
um like animals is intuitive
um or wolf packs because we have dogs
and we can see they try to align
maybe something about their emotional
state with
their human owners or with other dogs
you have in your house and you can see
that
maybe with wolves but when you bring up
ants that's interesting
because outside of like the movie
ant-man don't really prescribe emotions
to them
um but there's definitely an alignment
of
their action states like in terms of
which chemical pathways they're going to
follow
um and when they leave these chemical
traces that say
um there's definitely food here more and
more ants travel there's more and more
chemical traces and as the food's
depleted the trace
goes away so even though there's that
really close physical proximity
there's still some knowledge
of the other instrumental states in
their coordinated
behavior and so it's it's interesting
to kind of make that jump from behavior
to actually ascribing
i want my mental state to match yours in
some way
and the way that that gets manifested
through feedback with the environment or
stigmergy in the social insects
the way that somebody might decorate a
tea room and it's very serene
it's like when you're in this space i i
you know i want you to be synchronized
on this
mental alignment this is a sacred space
or this is a messy spot
and then similarly when you were just
talking about the traces in the ant
colony which fundamentally
are serving to reduce the uncertainty of
the colony about where to get food
in that case and the way that the ants
can communicate with each other
is through direct touch tactile touch
and olfaction
as well as these long-term traces which
can
uh potentially generate something like
collective mental state
and so these are really interesting
questions like does the worker
have a prior is that the mental state
that's being uh shared or
doesn't want it to be shared or is it
that
individuals who act in a way that lead
to coherent colonies
we end up seeing them over evolutionary
time more
so it's almost independent of whether
there's this experiential component
to the adaptive prior it's almost
whether it is
adaptive is this sort of circular
question kind of like survival of the
fittest
we're going to see packs of animals or
packs of single cell bacteria or
insects that end up having aligned and
adaptive and effective communication
and then what does that actually tell us
because we're only going to see those
systems persist
we're only going to see communication as
a dysfunction
in mostly functional systems because
things just didn't randomly show up here
one way or the other
i i think you nailed it with that
statement that it's a circular argument
in a way um i was thinking about that
re-reading the paper as well
it's like wow this sounds just too clean
um like like it all it all kind of makes
sense
in the direction that this argument is
going um
and uh back to the point about um
how we as humans interpret what other
species are doing
to be communicative uh cooperation
or not is you know a whole nother
question because
um if if it's furthering their means um
as a species then they're
cooperating the right amount um
there's a line about um how uh
even great apes um they do
pointing but in a way that's not um
communicative cooperation but more
selfish
and i wonder if that's just kind of a
human um
our human species uh bias on
how other species communicate not as
good as we do
yep and to bring this actually to
narratives and
narrative attunement the action patterns
from a mechanical standpoint that humans
are being
asked to do by each other are too
complicated to just be
hard-coded or directly you can't say hey
move your left hand a little bit up
okay now go a little bit down now go
back to where you were and go okay so
you can't tell someone
here's how you draw the letter a okay
now here's how you draw the next letter
you tell them the next level of would be
write the word
uh alexandra and then they're going to
interpret that unpack that in their own
way and then an even higher level of
narrative attunement would be like
i want you to do this or here's why it's
important that you should do this
and so if you can get people to be
aligned at the here's why it's important
to
go out and do community service towards
this end then
they're going to figure out all the
details with getting in and out of the
car
and turning left at the stoplight and
coming to all these details
that you would spend your whole life
trying to micromanage
if you can provide narrative attunement
then each individual agent is going to
unpack that in their own niche
in a way that makes sense to them and so
it's a very high leverage point
to be able to specify and attune
narratives because people who are
narratively aligned with you
will act in a similar way they'll
respond to stimuli in a way that's
similar to yourself or at least
beneficial
in a broad coalition and that's a um
avenue or a vector for attunement of
action in humans
that is not as developed potentially in
other species
which comes back to this question about
human-specific
is it really human-specific to be having
an adaptive prior that communication is
useful
well it's different in uh degree
there's no other species with such an
extent of digital or written
communication
but is it really different in type when
we have turn taking
rhythmic coordination across the animal
and even non-animal
kingdom so cool stuff there
any thoughts on attention or attunement
before we get to
attention
all right i just want to say maybe
[Music]
should we or is it possible to
separate maybe for like a signal level
and for i don't know content level
so to have a good tournament
you first for example need to exchange
some kind of
special signals to start the
main part of this tournament
yep and that relates to these ostentive
cubes
so if in a uh email the first
line is to whom it may concern it's a
relatively formal way
it's saying this is a cue i'm showing
you my hand right at the beginning i
speak english
i speak formally etc versus there's
other ostensive cues
that could attune somebody hey just a
quick message
um these are different cues and then
there's the level of syntactic
attunement that's making sure that the
message comes across
just from a bitwise perspective and then
there's the semantic
attunement the meaning of the message
but of course the media is the message
so there's like somewhat of a blurring
between the
um content and the delivery mechanism
and then there's the narrative
attunement which is at the highest level
that goes beyond any single meme the
jpeg or the words in it or whatever
it's that higher level attunement that
actually dictates how humans respond
sasha
i just wanted to comment a bit on the
the
what where do our priors go wrong and
um if this is a bit of a meta comment uh
maybe you'll see in the recording but
um as we're working towards alignment um
of mental states uh your video and audio
are not aligned
and um
in the adaptive sense um or in the
evolutionary sense like
oh go ahead go ahead oh and
in the evolutionary sense like i i want
to make sure that uh your voice and
video
are aligned because that would never
happen outside of a video chat
but in a video chat i don't need to
worry that they're offset
because i'm listening to your voice for
the content of what you're saying
um so that those two things are not
aligned
is actually okay in this scenario but is
still
um concerning and draws my attention to
that uh mismatch
yep that's a deep prior that we've
learned by
communicating in person that definitely
gets violated also people being
pixelated in person i don't i don't
remember that happening but
it did happen from time to time so here
on the
attention question so here's another
quote from the paper and i really liked
this because it it brought a connection
from so-called folk psychology or just
everyday
discussions of topics that are
neurophysiological
into what is going to be bringing us
towards a more formal phrasing of the
question
they wrote in active inference the folk
psychological term attention refers to
two
distinct but closely related phenomena
the first one is
epistemic value and the second one is
precision weighting there's a citation
there
epistemic value salience or affordance
is the component of policy selection
just discussed
it is the component of the value of
policies that tracks how much a policy
reduces uncertainty about the state of
the world
it provides a description of the folk
psychological phenomena of actively
orienting towards or
turning one's attention to a certain
modality or part of the sensory field
for example through
visual stockades that sample particular
locations in visual space
in short salience or epistemic
affordance is an attribute of how we
sample the world
in the sense that actively sampling
sensory information will reduce
uncertainty in relation to our current
beliefs
in contrast this is the second type of
attention precision is an attribute of
sensory data per se
of itself imprecise sensory data should
have less effect on bayesian belief
updating relative to precise information
it is therefore important to afford the
right precision to each sensory sample
via precision weighting so
here's the two questions i asked about
this quote people can
answer one of the questions or ask a
further question about this paragraph or
bring up their own interpretation how is
this idea of attention
related to ascent of cues and how is
related to culture as an informational
niche
so first we can think about what are
these two different kinds of attention
because they talk about how there's two
distinct but closely related phenomena
so we're going to reduce our uncertainty
about this term attention
and it's broken down into two categories
the epistemic
value which relates to the value of
knowledge and then
precision weighting which is like the
value of the sensory data itself
and we can go to this last sentence to
look at how they differ pretty
specifically
imprecise sensory data should have less
effect on bayesian belief updating
relative to precise information so let's
imagine if someone says okay i'm going
to turn on this tv
and it's going to have the results of
the election and you turn on the tv
and it's just static now there's many
kinds of static
but the point is with respect to the
question that you want to reduce your
uncertainty about
imprecise sensory data or if your eyes
are very blurry or if you can't hear
what the speaker is saying
this kind of sensory data that's garbled
shouldn't
be used to update your beliefs about the
world
at a deep level so this is kind of
getting to this question
of uh the syntactic versus the semantic
attunement
because in the sense of precision
waiting
if you're paying attention to a stimulus
in free energy
that means that that stimulus is rising
all the way up to the top of the
attentional
salience hierarchy uh in a sense it's
really it's touching your deep priors
in a way that's influencing them
meaningfully whereas
things that aren't being paid attention
to in the sense of precision waiting
are the sensory inputs that don't make a
difference for your deep priors
so i'm not paying attention to how my
sock feels in my
shoe until i am but i'm not paying
attention to it in the sense that
the precision weighting is very uh low
even though it's a valid sensory input
it's just the the attention being paid
to that stimuli is low
but the value of that information about
the foot
can also be thought of as relatively low
within this epistemic value
sense of attention so if someone says
pay attention
fifty percent of this is like that it's
like saying
this is an important piece of knowledge
so yes you also need to have the
epistemic
uh content it's not just enough to get
the jpeg across
completely or to have somebody hear your
words there's this
epistemic value to certain things that
are said
and a way that this is related to
ostensive cues is just with the
simple phrase hey pay attention or
listen up
the next thing i'm going to say is
important these are broad
ways that are they're ascentive cues
they're demonstrated
cues that people can use linguistically
or non-linguistically like waving or
things like that
these are cues that say hey if you can
make out this signal
if you can hear my sos if you can see me
waving
then please pay attention because this
next thing i'm about to convey
is not just uh syntactically important
but it's actually epistemically
important
thoughts on this
uh yeah it seems interesting because
when i uh read this paper i also use a
red
highlight to this part about folk
differences between folk psychology term
and because usually i use yellow and for
this part
i decided to use red one because it's
really it looks like
very important for communication and
understanding it
and as we know from
figures and from this paper about
regimes of attention what
which are very important to have
to really have generation and
synchronization
of mental states uh so and if you want
to speak
about uh just how this to set up
this regime of attention and maybe
as it usually usually discussed in
psychology like
how to train attention and
to manage attention uh we should
to see this difference because between
epistemic
part and this precision weighting
very nice and so if we
uh how it could related to ostensive
cues
[Music]
i think about i don't know how is a
concept
about attention governance so some kind
of
rules to manage attention and some kind
proofs which ostensive cues is
really important and which one ones is
not important or maybe wrong for example
yep and special uh signs that say hey i
didn't
hear what you said you lagged out could
you repeat that i needed i needed
more precision waiting on what you said
because i couldn't even get to your
epistemic content and then
oh wait i heard you on what the name was
i just i don't know who that author is
so that's the epistemic level or okay i
know that author
but i still don't understand how this is
fitting into the narrative of why we're
in this conversation
it's another level saying i got you
epistemically but now narratively i'm a
bit lost
and so these are different levels that
could be quantified
and could be formalized and de-risked as
well
um anything else go ahead sasha
yeah another thing to add about
ostensive cues
i think this answers the one of the
questions
posed in the paper which is how might an
individual recognize
another's intention to generate an
active communication
intended for oneself in the first place
and um that was another question that i
had written out as
as interesting and it seems like kind of
comes back full circle to answer it
that um ostensive cues are
a way to let our
to let other people know that we're
intending to communicate with them
in a more um multi-level way
like to focus their attention first
before we communicate the uh
important information and then to the
point about
uh rules of attention at least from
a neuroscience background which i think
shies away
a bit from understanding the
psychology of the human experience and
tries to have a more deflationary
account of uh what's happening
the rules i as i've heard them at least
of attention
um is to try to unpack and understand
why a human is attending um
to a certain stimulus or not
versus how a human can modulate their
attention
so that they can better attend or um pay
attention uh
based on what they want to accomplish so
it's a bit of internal versus um
external perception of what human
attention
is so i like that point about
the psychology perspective on this
because
ultimately that's a a bit more useful
for um
individuals making choices than to
understand what's happening from the
outside
yep the precision psychiatry
work fristen and babcock and others
talks a lot about
these aberrant precision errors and
about how they result in decision making
or experienced pathologies so in this
last
section i think we could actually even
go one more level
into this epistemic value topic
and bring it to free energy so this is
again about active inference as a
process theory
and we can see the minimal active
inference loop here
but i think this is going to be an
opportunity for us to kind of go up
the the chain another dimension which is
to go from this active inference
loop which is very qualitative and like
the skeleton
of action and let's look at a quote from
the authors about
where does free energy play into this so
the authors write
the free energy expected under a policy
tracks the probability of that
particular policy being pursued
i.e of that specific policy being
selected to guide action
so it's kind of weird when people think
well wait what is my brain doing
inference on it's
doing inference on the probability that
right now i'm in a chair i mean don't i
just know i'm in a chair or
don't i just know that it's likely to be
me in a chair in 20 minutes if that's
where i want to be or not
but no actually what's happening is the
brain is doing inference
on the probability of a policy being
pursued
relatively less expected free energy
indicates a relatively more probable
policy
and this is seen sometimes not to go
into too many details but when people
take the log or the negative log
of a probability it's just so that you
can minimize a number
and by getting closer to zero which is
like a fixed number
we can know that we're maximizing the
probability so
if we make it so that smaller numbers
are more likely like
one over the likelihood type thing then
we can actually do a minimization
problem
going towards zero as a lower bound
because some of these things being
bounded by zero and then know that we're
making more probable or better policy
decisions by minimizing
whereas if we were to do a maximization
problem and just say well let's just
maximize the overall likelihood
there's no known upper bound for how
optimal it could be
so you might not know when to stop but
minimization helps you because it kind
of
puts a hard stop on zero expected free
energy
can be decomposed into two terms so here
we come back there's epistemic
and there's going to be another one the
two terms are epistemic value
which is the information gain of an
observation and pragmatic value
which is the expected log evidence of an
outcome
given a generative model of how outcomes
depend on action
the relative influence of each term
quantifies the degree to which a
particular policy
generates actions that explore the niche
i.e exploration
or actions that leverage reliable
expectations about the niche
to secure preferred outcomes i.e
exploitation
this is depicted in figure one so any
thoughts on this or there's a lot more
to say here
one channel isn't going i was just going
to say that explanation you gave for why
it's a minimization problem um was
really helpful like in a really lay
sense of
just that minimization is an easier
computation that has a lower bound that
was
a really helpful explanation thanks alex
i i just want to point uh one thing
about
what these terms of exploration and
exploitation
is also could be met in some literature
about
business strategies so it's possible
ways to
accompany and to choose
direction to act on different stages and
different states and
you as it wrote it in this literature
you should
the company should first to
explorate some your idea and the next
step
is exploration exploitation if there is
some value
for the company great and we'll come
back
to that in in just a second it's it's so
true it's a lot like explore exploit in
other
domains and if you go too far onto one
end
it ends up being less than useful if
it's purely exploratory
ever exploiting anything then you never
extract the value that would be like
searching for where the oil is but never
drilling and then
on the other hand if you're just like
wait there's oil right here i'm gonna
exploit
you're gonna find out that that well is
going to run dry and you won't have put
in enough
research and development into
exploration and so
there's no simple answer as to whether
it's better to be exploratory or
exploitative at what level
um that's what free energy is about and
i thought this could be a good
opportunity to actually connect
what is free energy why is it called
free energy if it's just the probability
of a particular policy being pursued
why don't we just call it the
probability of a policy being pursued
and to answer this i'm going to draw on
a little bit of
chemistry a little bit of statistical
mechanics
so the term free energy in the usage of
fristen
has less to do with the tesla sense of
free energy
like electricity for everybody and has
more to do with this
sense of gibbs free energy which is a
thermodynamic characteristic
and we can look at this equation the
total gives free energy
equals u minus ts plus pv and in
chemical terms
these do have physical interpretations
like the absolute temperature in kelvin
or the entropy measured in some other
unit but
the idea that i want to get across with
this equation
is just that you can partition you can
have an expected free energy of some
chemical reaction
and that even though it's a total
singular number it can be partitioned
into for example the internal energy of
the system chemically
the temperature weighted final entropy
of the system and the pressure weighted
final volume
let's look at how this plays out in
chemistry
so on the left on the top
we have an exergonic reaction or a
reaction where the delta
g is below zero so it's a there's some
big differences between
gibbs free energy and frisk's conception
not the least of which that
free energy as it's being discussed
previously it's bounded at zero
but delta g gives free energy it
actually works in a little bit different
way where values that are below zero
means that the reactants have more
energy than the products
so these are exothermic or heat
releasing reactions
and then conversely if the delta g is
greater than zero
that means that the reactants have to
basically go uphill
and so we can look at this reaction
coordinate graph
and whether you're going downhill
overall
on the left side or uphill overall like
a non-spontaneous or
endergonic reaction in both cases you
need to come over this
hump that's the activation energy
barrier
and that's why certain reactions happen
at high temperature but they don't
happen at low temperature
it's like a ball that's right here but
it doesn't have enough energy to get
over the hill
so it's like even though the candle is
thermodynamically favored to burn
otherwise it wouldn't burn it's not
going to spontaneously combust because
it doesn't have the activation energy to
burn and then
if you're going uphill anyway then it's
an
even higher hill to climb because really
you have to climb up over
your final end point and then drop back
down in a way that's thermodynamically
favored
and so again it's kind of a metaphor at
this point but there is math that we're
just not going into
we can look at this delta g partitioning
of the system
and again delta g doesn't capture
everything about the system it doesn't
mention the activation energy it doesn't
mention
other things about the stoichiometry of
the reaction but it is something that
can be partitioned
and then similarly we can think about
this expected free energy
in the first instance and we just heard
it discussed as being partitioned
into two things the epistemic and the
pragmatic
value so the uh knowledge or exploratory
value
of a policy and then the pragmatic or
the exploitative
value of uh policy and then
we can uh just directly link it to that
uh
language around explore and exploit as
well as around uh divergent
and convergent thinking so
these are still a little bit
metaphorical but
i thought it would be interesting just
to directly contrast
the free energy from thermophysics
basically and from chemistry
and then note how this partitioning of
expected free energy into multiple terms
has a lot of carryover from
chemistry and from physics any thoughts
on this
or we have more math that we can survey
to
cool let's just go back to this figure
with
the outline that we've looked at a lot
and let's actually
look at these equations and not to um
derive them or to implement them but
let's just look at
what are these equations because we've
talked a lot about how
there's internal states and there's
external states we've talked about how
sensations are what enter the markov
blanket and how actions
guided by policy are what exit the
markov blanket
and so this is the minimal loop of
embodied inactive cognition
okay so where do we go from the
qualitative theory
of just saying hey ecological cognition
means it's always this action
embodied feedback loop how are we going
to add a layer of math
and move towards formalization of this
so we can just
look at the equations that are in each
of these four
categories and what we can see here is
what action is doing is minimizing the
agents bound on surprise
and this equation again even though it
could be expanded into
larger formats later the two pieces
are basically the complexity of the
action
and the expected accuracy you'll also
note that there's a ton of things where
it's like wait
you're calculating the expected free
energy not just the free energy itself
and the reason for that is the actual
values
are inaccessible to the organism and so
the computation or the inference that
the organism
is actually doing is like not where is
my leg
it's where do i expect my leg to be
and that's the genesis of things like
the ghost limb syndrome
all these phenomena that don't quite
make sense in a sensory relay paradigm
if you make it about a second order
expectation
where do i expect to be now it's now
casting
and it turns out that where am i now how
would you even know
where you were but if you ask where do i
expect to be
and how confident am i about that
expectation
it turns out that is what gets good
enough and does it in a really
computationally attractive way
so action is minimizing the agents bound
on surprise
by balancing or combining we won't go
too much
into detail there the expected
complexity of the action
versus the accuracy of the action and so
one way to think about that is
complex actions like playing the piano
are difficult
to perform unless there's a feeling that
there's also going to be accuracy
whereas very low complexity movements
like flailing one's arms
maybe are done without worrying too much
about the accuracy of the motion
and then on the perception in the
internal state the yellow
box we have the um the
internal states are reflected by the the
kl divergence which is the informational
divergence
between the priors and the posterior so
that reflects
how the worldview is being updated and
then it's penalized by the surprisal
and um yeah i just want to
put it out there just there is a layer
of mathematics and equations that go
beyond
the structure of active inference and
then just these last two
boxes before we kind of summarize and
close out
it it frames external states the niche
construction of the external states
as bounding the uh surprise
and so again it looks this green box the
equation with kl divergence minus the
surprise
it should remind you a lot of this
yellow box which is also the kl
divergence minus the surprise
and that's because this system is
actually
symmetric with respect to whether the
external states are
the human or whether the external states
are the world
because in the end it's a bi-directional
markov blanket with sense and action
moving both directions
and so it would be a little bit weird if
depending on which system we decided was
internal to the markov blanket
it went one way and if we put the system
on the other side it'd be the other way
so this is the the work that's been
built out in the
variational ecology work of actual
constant
and others where it's realizing that
hey the niche especially when it's just
other agents
it's actually like the markov blanket
gives us this symmetry and so the
internal state equations look a lot like
the external state equations
and then sensations minimize the agents
bound on surprise
and again this is complexity minus
accuracy
which looks a lot like the complexity
minus accuracy in red of action
because the senses coming in are the
active states of the world and so
similarly we we have this penalization
of the complexity versus the accuracy of
sensation
and that should remind you of earlier
when we were talking about the the value
of communication
if the input is garbled then the
sensations
um it's not even that they're surprising
or not they're just not that useful for
us
and so there's a lot of parallels
between the different
states in this model um across the
divide of the marcotte blanket as well
as the two types of things that pierce
through the markov blanket
and so just first coat of paint to close
out
this discussion with a little bit of the
math underlying the formalisms of active
inference
cool so any
overall thoughts or
just a comment on that last slide um i
kind of braced myself for the equations
but
i i think that's actually very useful to
talk through them
and you did a great job
really drawing those parallels out and i
would actually love to see more of that
in future discussions
about linking the papers back to the
equations
in sort of these layman's terms
cool well we'll definitely need
assistance
but it's good to try it's good to try
it was also really nice that reef little
um
marriage of your action states are the
world or the other agents
sensory states and then their action
states are your sensory states
um which i mean it's shown in the
pictures
but sort of it's not always internalized
that this is like super perspectival so
it depends on
from which um agent you're looking and
it's also putting some
agentive sort of characteristics on the
world or the ego niche
that you're interacting inside
yep very nice it's really a fully
relational
theory because there's no objective
internal states
you can say well the internal states are
internal to my epithelium
it's like okay you can choose that as
your system of interest from an
engineering perspective you can choose
that to be the bounds of your markov
blanket if you define it appropriately
but there's no way that you're going to
be able to say that that's unambiguously
the singular system of analysis it's
just markov blankets all the way down
and then when you think about um let's
say contact improv
or turn taking and conversation in both
of these cases
there's the whole world but we can kind
of zoom in on these the dyad that's
interacting
and then you're right for them the
external state
is being the generative part of the
external state is like the other person
and that's what's generating the
coordination between the two arms
from which you're receiving sensory
input from
and so one person is doing inference on
the sensory state of another and this
kind of ties us back to this idea of
alignment of mental states
so maybe let's look at one of the um
figures here we are in the world
and so yes it could be that two people
are paying attention to the same
world so here's like one person writes
on the whiteboard
and that contributes to changing the
informational niche
this person sees what's on the
whiteboard they think ah what did they
mean
by this they add something new to the
whiteboard or they say something
that contributes to the niche and you
get this infinity loop um
or you can actually almost cut out the
middleman here and just
fuse those two parts you have two
individuals and one person's action
states are
received as sensory information by the
other person and that's why the
alignment of mental state is
so important because we can't just align
people on
each syllable by syllable we have to
align people on semantic
content of what is being conveyed and
then even higher
we have to align people to really a
narrative understanding of what's
happening
because there's never going to be enough
time to um convey all those micro state
details
and that's why this is so cool to see
that the mathematics reflects that
symmetry
and the symmetry is what allows us to be
fully relational
without taking an absolutist perspective
on what the correct system of analysis
is for communication so communication is
fully
um relational it's all about those edges
between nodes
and then now we have this mathematical
framework where we can
talk about the nodes and edges in a way
that gives them
their due
cool um any closing thoughts
otherwise this was a super interesting
conversation
uh i just wanted to highlight again
the importance of this description
of attention in a more formal way
and from perspective of active inference
so as we see if
this part of attention is important to
communication and communication is
important to alignment and
it's a basement alignment of mental
states
so maybe for future discussion we need
to unpack
this part more deeply about attention
great i think um it would be cool to
look at
perhaps a mathematical treatment of
attention in a multi-level
scheme and i think i know a good paper
for that because i agree
if the person isn't paying attention to
the syntax
if they can't hear the story they're not
going to get it
if they can't get the words they're not
gonna get it if they can't get the
narrative
they're not gonna get it and and so or
they're gonna get something but what it
is that they get may not be what the
speaker intends
and so how do we formal model this and
how can active inference
help us cut through some of these
complexities and
simplify the whole system in a way that
we could actually
impact the systems that we want to
impact by designing attention
uh regimes um and culture in the way
that we want to make it
cool very great stuff everyone thanks so
much
for this follow-up active stream 3.5
part two i think i'll try to find a way
to
fuse these two streams and
we really appreciate everybody who's
listening and providing us feedback
and coming out to discuss with us so
thank you
everyone and i'm gonna terminate the
live stream thank you